<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The royall passing-bell: or, Dauids summons to the graue A sermon preached (lately) in the parish-church of Orchard-Portman in Sommerset. At the funerall of the most hopefull, and truely-noble, Sr. Hugh Portman, baronet; the great losse and sorrow both of his name and countrie. By Humphrey Sydenham, Master of Arts, late fellow of Wadham Colledge in Oxford.</title>
            <author>Sydenham, Humphrey, 1591-1650?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13270</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23571</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118111</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853320</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853320</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18696</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13270)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18696)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1222:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The royall passing-bell: or, Dauids summons to the graue A sermon preached (lately) in the parish-church of Orchard-Portman in Sommerset. At the funerall of the most hopefull, and truely-noble, Sr. Hugh Portman, baronet; the great losse and sorrow both of his name and countrie. By Humphrey Sydenham, Master of Arts, late fellow of Wadham Colledge in Oxford.</title>
                  <author>Sydenham, Humphrey, 1591-1650?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26, 29-38, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W. Stansby, for Nathaniel Butter,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Dom. 1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Also issued as part of "Sermons by Humph. Sydenham" (STC 23572).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18696:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18696:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE ROYALL PASSING-BELL: OR, DAVIDS SVMMONS to the GRAVE. A Sermon preached (lately) in the Pariſh-Church of <hi>Orchard-Portman</hi> in SOMMERSET. <hi>At the Funerall of the moſt hopefull, and</hi> truely-noble, S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. HVGH PORTMAN, <hi>Baronet;</hi> the great loſſe and ſorrow both of his <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>Countrie.</hi> By HVMPHREY SYDENHAM, Maſter of <hi>Arts,</hi> late Fellow of <hi>Wadham</hi> Colledge in OXFORD.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Qui virtutem alterius publicarivult, virtuti laborat, non gloria.</hi> 
               <bibl>ANT. SEN.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>W. Stansby,</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Butter. An. Dom.</hi> 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18696:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18696:2"/>
            <head>TO MY DESERVEDLY honour'd, IOHN HELE, of <hi>Wembury,</hi> Eſquire; the great hope of his NAME, and expectation of his COVNTRY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His flies not to you for <hi>peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall</hi> barely, and <hi>ſuruey,</hi> but for <hi>protection;</hi> I want not a a <hi>Reader,</hi> but a <hi>Vindicator;</hi> ſuch a one, as can aſwell <hi>iuſtifie</hi> Jnnocence, as <hi>ſhrine</hi> it: an <hi>Agent</hi> remark'd, no leſſe for <hi>Goodnes,</hi> than for <hi>Power.</hi> And, in this my Appeale to <hi>Worth</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> J ſincerely wiſh, that, whileſt I a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wake your <hi>Charity,</hi> I pull not on you <hi>Enuy,</hi> or <hi>Diſhonour;</hi> 'tis not my <hi>intention,</hi> but my <hi>feare.</hi> For, amongſt other my weake endeuours
<pb facs="tcp:18696:3"/>which haue formerly aduanc'd me to the <hi>vnde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued applauſe</hi> of many. <hi>This</hi> had the <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to diſpleaſe,</hi> and I thinke it not my <hi>wound,</hi> but my <hi>Glory.</hi> Impartiall diſcourſes are equally <hi>blunt,</hi> and <hi>honeſt;</hi> and tho ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, they haue their reliſh and farewell in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſt, yet that is their <hi>Crowne,</hi> and not their <hi>Fate.</hi> Howeuer, an <hi>affected Stoiciſme</hi> I euer loath'd, and not onely as a <hi>Stoiciſme,</hi> but as <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected.</hi> There is nothing ſo open to contempt and laughter, as a <hi>compos'd ſullenneſſe.</hi> 'Tis true, a natiue roughnes and auſteritie of language, I haue pupill'd from my youth, That's <hi>mine owne,</hi> J confeſſe, but I dote not on it; my <hi>Child</hi> but I lull it not; and therefore, if it ſometimes proue way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and offenſiue, <hi>Nature</hi> praevaricates, and not <hi>will.</hi> I was neuer yet guiltie of a premedita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted treſpaſſe on mens Names, or Honours; J haue neither ſo much <hi>time</hi> for rancour, nor <hi>diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> or had I both, I ſhould haue here ſtrangled them for <hi>his</hi> deare memory, to whom I owed, not onely my ſeruices, but <hi>my ſelfe.</hi> Hee was nobly your <hi>Aſſociate,</hi> (my honoured Sir) and (for J muſt ſtill boaſt in the liuery) my <hi>Maſter;</hi> nay, my <hi>Patron;</hi> and, what is higher yet, my <hi>friend,</hi> my <hi>vnſhaken friend.</hi> Theſe haue ſo ingag'd me
<pb facs="tcp:18696:3"/>both in <hi>Ciuill</hi> and <hi>Religious</hi> bonds, that ſhould I labour to diſſolue either by any Reall affront, or diſcourteſie to <hi>his Tribe,</hi> I were neither <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall man,</hi> nor <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> and yet, loe, I am more than both, a <hi>Diuine;</hi> but, a <hi>ſaucie one</hi> ('tis ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour'd) and a <hi>Cruell;</hi> a <hi>ſordid</hi> alſo, and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptuous;</hi> and, (O my impoſſible guilt! my vniuſt calamitie!) a <hi>falſe one,</hi> and <hi>vnthankfull.</hi> Such Liueries I can weare with as much <hi>patience</hi> as the the former, tho not <hi>triumph;</hi> and yet theſe, againe are not my <hi>Croſſe,</hi> but my <hi>Laurell;</hi> I grow <hi>greene</hi> in the opinion of mine owne <hi>inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, tho</hi> wither, perhaps, in the Reſpects of others; who, if they were not ſo hot as to rauiſh words vnnaturally, and force them from the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt intentions of the Speaker, they ſhould finde, I am a <hi>Leuite,</hi> ſtill, and not a <hi>Libeller;</hi> and, what I preach'd, was not an <hi>Inuectiue,</hi> but a <hi>Sermon.</hi> Me thinkes, it is neither <hi>Charitie,</hi> nor <hi>Iudgement</hi> in a hearer, to wreſt <hi>Diuinity</hi> to the diſuantage of his owne honour; 'twas n'ere my Cuſtome to rubbe harſhly, on particulars; my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofes were, as they ſhould be, <hi>of ſinnes,</hi> and not of <hi>Perſons;</hi> and <hi>thoſe</hi> too, ran <hi>generally,</hi> which no Circumſtances can reduce to <hi>paticulars,</hi> but where the Parties are either <hi>preiudicate,</hi> or
<pb facs="tcp:18696:4"/>
               <hi>guiltie;</hi> And, if any ſuch I met with (as I hope I did not) let them learne to <hi>reforme,</hi> and not to <hi>cenſure;</hi> and thanke him for his home-ſpun ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſements, who was rather a <hi>Remembran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer</hi> of their errors, than <hi>a Iudge.</hi> This is the way to reſeue their <hi>honour,</hi> and my <hi>innocence;</hi> which, as it hath beene euer taught to magnifie worth in others; ſo, to preſume on yours, that, when you haue read impartially <hi>this ſad peece of mine,</hi> you will ſay that I haue beene a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Seruant to <hi>my</hi> dead friend, and <hi>yours,</hi> whoſe noble reſpects to mee, I haue found to ſuruiue in you; whom, for many ſolid and materiall fauours, I am captiu'd to obſerue, whileſt I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours moſt thankfully deuoted, HVM. SYDENHAM.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18696:4"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE <hi>Edward</hi> Lord <hi>Howard,</hi> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron of <hi>Eſcrick,</hi> my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Honourable good LORD.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen you were pleaſed, the other yeare, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit me your <hi>Chaplaine,</hi> I had intended, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd my paraemetiall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations to your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> from the <hi>Pulpit;</hi> But I was, then, preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a ſudden, and ſeuere <hi>ſickneſſe,</hi> which hath, hitherto, diſabled me to tender you any thing that way. Now, becauſe I would
<pb facs="tcp:18696:5"/>not be obnoxious to a double miſ-conceit, I preſent you this <hi>peece</hi> from the <hi>Preſſe,</hi> that your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> may <hi>reade,</hi> and ſo <hi>remember</hi> the <hi>record,</hi> both of my <hi>deuotions,</hi> and <hi>endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours.</hi> I heartily <hi>wiſh</hi> I were ſo compleatly <hi>recouer'd</hi> for <hi>attendance,</hi> that I might as well <hi>ſpeake,</hi> as <hi>write</hi> my <hi>labours;</hi> and then (perhaps) I ſhould better ſatisfie your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> then in this <hi>common kind;</hi> which hath made <hi>many</hi> of my <hi>Profeſsion</hi> (and may <hi>mee</hi>) <hi>ridiculous.</hi> But I feare my infirmities, and therefore, as I muſt begge the honourable <hi>charitie</hi> of your <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience,</hi> ſo of your <hi>Protection</hi> alſo. For as I was, at firſt, a <hi>ſuiter</hi> for your <hi>ſeruice,</hi> (In which I haue cauſe to glorie) both for the <hi>greatneſſe</hi> and <hi>goodneſſe</hi> of your <hi>ſelfe,</hi> and <hi>name</hi>) ſo I am, ſtill for the <hi>graces</hi> of it: and doe hope, that when you haue made a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler <hi>enquiry,</hi> who I am, and where I haue ſpent my <hi>time,</hi> and <hi>talent;</hi> your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> will not diſdaine to <hi>owne,</hi> and <hi>honour</hi> mee with your ſucceding <hi>fauours.</hi> In a word (my <hi>noble Lord</hi>) I ſhall not forget <hi>what</hi> you haue made <hi>mee,</hi> nor the <hi>dutie</hi> enioyn'd me by <hi>it:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:18696:5"/>I will pray for <hi>you,</hi> for your <hi>Lady,</hi> for your <hi>little Ones,</hi> and for the <hi>growth,</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance</hi> of the houſe begun in <hi>you;</hi> and what elſe is requir'd in a <hi>religious obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uance,</hi> you ſhall ſurely find in the <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>loyaltie</hi> of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips humble ſeruant,</hi> Hum. Sydenham.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:18696:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The ſeuerall Texts, and names</hi> of the Sermons herein contained.</head>
            <p n="1">I. The Royall Paſſing-Bell: or <hi>Dauids</hi> Summons to the Graue.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>The Text. PSAL. 32.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thou haſt made my dayes as a ſpan-long, and mine Age is nothing before thee; Surely, euery man, in his beſt ſtate is altogether vanitie.</p>
            </q>
            <p n="2">II. The Rich mans Warning Peece.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>The Text. PSAL. 62.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>If Riches increaſe, ſet not thy heart vpon them.</p>
            </q>
            <p n="3">III. Waters of <hi>Marah</hi> and <hi>Meribah,</hi> or the ſower of Bitterneſſe, and Strife, Sweetned and Allayed.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>The Text. ROM 12.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>I beſeech you, Brethren, by the mercies of God, to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer vp your Bodies, a liuing Sacrifice, Holy, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to God which is your reaſonable ſeruice.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18696:6"/>
            <head>THE ROYALL PASSING-BELL: OR, <hi>DAVIDS SVMMONS</hi> to the GRAVE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>TEXT.</hi> Pſal. <hi>39.</hi> v. <hi>6.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Thou haſt made my dayes as a ſpan-long and mine Age is as nothing before thee; ſurely, euery man, <hi>in his beſt ſtate,</hi> is altogether vanitie.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE <hi>Text</hi> is a ſad Story of man's frailtie here; And 'tis a <hi>Prophet's,</hi> and a <hi>King's;</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> as mightie in <hi>Religion,</hi> as in <hi>valour;</hi> one that knew as well how to tune his <hi>ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes,</hi> as his <hi>triumphs,</hi> and had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten warbled ſweetly to them both, and ſung many a dainty <hi>Antheme</hi> in his <hi>Iſraell;</hi> ſo that, here wants neither <hi>eloquence,</hi> nor <hi>ſtate;</hi> nothing that may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade an auditorie, or awe it. I need not begge then either your <hi>patience</hi> or <hi>attention;</hi> the one is enioyn'd you from a <hi>Prophet,</hi> the other from a <hi>King;</hi> a good
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:18696:7"/>
               <hi>Prophet,</hi> and a <hi>King, Dauid,</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> and the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> after <hi>Gods</hi> owne <hi>heart;</hi> whoſe words here are are as <hi>Compact,</hi> as they are <hi>powerfull,</hi> ſo ioynted and knit together in one piece (a <hi>piece</hi> ſo vniforme, and exact) that ſhould I diſranke or ſunder them, I muſt either deface this beautie, or deſtroy it. I take them then as I firſt found them in their rich <hi>pyle</hi> and <hi>fabricke;</hi> whereln I haue obſerued three <hi>ſtories</hi> or <hi>aſcents.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Dayes</hi> in the <hi>firſt;</hi> and theſe <hi>dayes</hi> meaſured, and in that meaſure, reſembled <hi>Inſtar pugilli;</hi> as a <hi>ſpan-length;</hi> and this <hi>length, punctnall,</hi> and prefixt, not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable by any power of man; for <hi>in poſuiſti, thou haſt made</hi> it ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> In the next; <hi>theſe Dayes,</hi> are an <hi>Age;</hi> and this <hi>Age;</hi> weigh'd and compar'd, fals light in the ſcale, <hi>tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam nihil,</hi> as nothing; not abſolutely <hi>nothing,</hi> but comparatiuely, <hi>Ante te, before thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> In the third; theſe <hi>Dayes,</hi> and this <hi>Age,</hi> are <hi>man's;</hi> not <hi>man's</hi> in his <hi>Autumne,</hi> or declination, but in his <hi>beſt ſtate;</hi> and <hi>man</hi> thus in his beſt ſtate is but <hi>vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie;</hi> no peice-meale <hi>vanitie;</hi> but <hi>omnimoda vanitas, altogether vanitie; man</hi> is altogether <hi>vanitie; man</hi> is ſo; not <hi>man</hi> in particular, <hi>this man,</hi> only; not I, <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> the Prophet, or the King; but <hi>vniuerſus homo, euery man;</hi> as well the <hi>Begger</hi> as the <hi>King,</hi> or the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet;</hi> all mand-kinde; <hi>euery man; euery man, in his beſt ſtate, is altogether vanitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus I haue ſhew'd you the <hi>front</hi> of the <hi>Text,</hi> and what it promiſe's in the rooms within; if not ſo fully as you expect, or deſire, pleaſe you to take a <hi>review;</hi> and then you may ſee, more at large; <hi>Dayes,</hi> in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18696:7"/>firſt part; theſe <hi>dayes,</hi> proportion'd; <hi>who</hi> did it: and <hi>how:</hi> and all this in a <hi>Tu poſuiſti,</hi> thou haſt made them; and thou haſt ſo made them that they are as a <hi>ſpan-long;</hi> there I beginne. <hi>Thou haſt make my dayes as a ſpan-long.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſpan-long.</head>
               <p>TO weigh the miſerie of things tranſitory,<note place="margin">Pars prima.</note> with the glory of others more permanent and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, is the moſt exact way to iudge of either; the life of <hi>oppoſites</hi> is in Comparing them, when the <hi>good</hi> ſeeme <hi>better;</hi> and the <hi>bad worſe.</hi> Our <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> therefore, in a deepe ſpeculation of the <hi>Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and the fraile rarities of his creatures here below, looking vp at length to the beautie of the Celeſtiall hoaſt, <hi>Sunne, moone, and ſtarres,</hi> brings vp <hi>man</hi> vnto to them; not to riuall <hi>their</hi> perfection, but to queſtion <hi>his;</hi> and, after ſome ſtand, and pauſe, in ſteed of <hi>Compariſon,</hi> makes an <hi>enquiry;</hi> a double one; firſt, <hi>what man is?</hi> and then, <hi>what is the ſonne of man?</hi> in his eighth <hi>Pſalme,</hi> the fourth <hi>verſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is <hi>Homo,</hi> and <hi>filius hominis,</hi> and both, in the text, haue their <hi>energia,</hi> and weight of <hi>emphaſis.</hi> The word <hi>enoſc,</hi> or <hi>enoſh,</hi> tranſlated, <hi>man,</hi> ſign fles <hi>miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum &amp; calamitoſum hominem</hi> (ſaith <hi>Muſculus</hi>) a man of calamitie, and ſorrow;<note place="margin">Muſc. in Pſal. <hi>8.4.</hi>
                  </note> and '<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> giu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n to all men as a remembrance of their mortality; ſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.20. <hi>Let the Heathens know that they bee Enoſe, men,</hi> mortall <hi>men.</hi> Moreouer, <hi>ſonne of man,</hi> hath in the roote. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam; vt primae originis admoneamur,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Muſc. ibid.</note> to minde vs of our carnall pedigree; and that our ſource and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring is but <hi>Adamah,</hi> and ſo all <hi>man</hi>-kinde, <hi>earthie.</hi> And therefore ſome tranſlations, following cloſely
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18696:8"/>the tracke of the originall,<note place="margin">Aynſworth. Pſal. <hi>8.4.</hi>
                  </note> read thus; <hi>what is ſorry man that thou remembreſt him, and the ſonne of Adam, that thou viſiteſt him?</hi> not what is man, that rare creature indued with wiſedome, and vnderſtanding, the <hi>Almightie's</hi> Maſter-piece, the Image of his maker, and modell of the <hi>vniuerſe?</hi> But, what is <hi>Enoſe?</hi> what is <hi>Adam?</hi> What, the ſonne of calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and ſorrow? the ſonne of earth and frailite? what is he? nay what is he not? what not of <hi>calamitie</hi> and <hi>earth?</hi> inſomuch that the patient man, vnder the groane and ſenſe of humane imperfections, and the dayly bruiſe of his manifold affliction, is driuen to his expoſtulation alſo, with a <hi>quid eſt homo,? what is man? Iob.</hi> 7.17. where we meet againe with the word <hi>Enoſc, miſellus homo, wretched man;</hi> and not nakedly the word, but a particle ioyn'd with it, not <hi>mah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bolduc. in Cap. Iob. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> but <hi>mi,</hi> (as <hi>Bolducus</hi> obſerues) <hi>non quis, ſed quid quaerere intendens,</hi> as if the enquiry look't not to the <hi>perſon,</hi> but his <hi>condition;</hi> not, <hi>who is man?</hi> but <hi>what</hi> he is? knowing that <hi>man</hi> is not only the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete, <hi>miſerable;</hi> but, the very abſtract <hi>miſery</hi> it ſelfe; ſuch a miſery as may bee an example, and preſident of all others. And, if we but obſerue the <hi>criticiſmes</hi> and curioſities of expoſitours vpon the word <hi>man,</hi> they are neither impertinent nor fruitleſſe; for wee ſhall neuer meet it through the whole current of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Story without ſome deſcant and paraphraſe from the <hi>Hebrew.</hi> To particular in that of <hi>Eſay,</hi> where (in one <hi>text</hi>) words of oppoſite ſignification maske vnder a ſingle <hi>antitheſis,</hi> as in the fifth of that <hi>Propheſie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bolduc. in cap. <hi>4.</hi> Iob. <hi>17.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Incuruabitur homo, &amp; humiliabitur vir, man ſhall be brought downe, and man ſhall be humbled. Homo,</hi> there, is in the originall, <hi>Adam, quod nomen
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18696:8"/>infirmitatis eſt,</hi> a name of crazines and languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Vir, Iſe,</hi> or <hi>Iſh, Heroem, magnum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> importans,</hi> which inuolues ſomething of eminence, &amp; renowne; and ſo our new tranſlation giues it,<note place="margin">Eſa. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>the meane man ſhall bee brought downe, and the mighty man ſhall bee humbled;</hi> ſo that let man bee of what condition or eſtate ſoeuer, hee ſhall not bee long in it, without <hi>a bringing downe,</hi> or <hi>an humbling.</hi> If he be <hi>Iſc, mighty</hi> in poſſeſſion and <hi>name; humiliabitur,</hi> he <hi>ſhal be hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled;</hi> if he be <hi>Adam,</hi> of courſe and popular condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo humble already, yet he muſt be lower, <hi>incuruabitur,</hi> hee <hi>ſhall bee brought downe;</hi> brought downe and humbled with a witneſſe, <hi>ad infernum,</hi> ſayes the <hi>Text,</hi> euen vnto <hi>Hell. Aperit infernus os ſuum,</hi> the 16. <hi>verſe</hi> of that <hi>Chapter.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſa.</hi> 5 16.</note> But <hi>Hell</hi> is the miſety of another <hi>Age;</hi> our Text hath little to doe with that, and ſo this place makes not for our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; but, the word <hi>Sheol</hi> will befriend vs here, and make this <hi>infernum,</hi> a graue, too, and thither we are humbled euery day; and then we aske no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more <hi>Quis?</hi> or <hi>quid eſt homo? who,</hi> or <hi>what is man?</hi> but, <hi>Vbi homo? where is man?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 14.10.</note> for ſo the penſiue man interrogates; <hi>man waſteth away, and giueth vp the ghoſt, and where is he? Iob.</hi> 14.10. where is hee? <hi>fuit, non vixit,</hi> he was here but now, but he is gone; gone from his <hi>Caluary</hi> to his <hi>Golgotha;</hi> his gall &amp; vinegar in his late agonie (the bitter Croſſe of his body) to his ſepulchre (here) he wed out of the rocke;<note place="margin">He was buried in a vault.</note> his bed ready made for him in the darke, where hee lie's downe, and riſes not, till this <hi>fuit</hi> hath put on a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrexit,</hi> this <hi>mortalitie,</hi> a <hi>reſurrection.</hi> And, ſeeing he is now gone, let vs no more aske, <hi>Quis? aut vbi?</hi>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:18696:9"/>who, or where <hi>man</hi> is? but once more, <hi>quid eſt</hi> what he is? or rather, what his <hi>Age</hi> is? or (if you pleaſe) what his dayes in that age? and then the text will anſwere by way of ſimilitude and reſemblance, <hi>Inſtar pugilli,</hi> as a <hi>ſpan-long.</hi> A ſhort time (no doubt) that is inch't out, or ſingred by the <hi>ſpan;</hi> other things remark't in holy ſtory, haue their dimenſions lin'd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out by the farhome, or the cubit, or the foot, at leaſt; nothing that I remember, by this fraile meaſure, but the life of <hi>man;</hi> a thing ſo fragile and momentany, that there was nothing to expreſſe it, but a <hi>ſpan;</hi> a word ſo tumbled by Expoſitours, that they are ſomewhat driuen to the plundge, to giue the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of it a proper ſignification in a ſecond language, and therefore ſome tranſlations haue it <hi>inſtar pugil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li;</hi> or, <hi>ad menſuram pugillorum,</hi> a <hi>little handfull;</hi> ſo <hi>Felix,</hi> and <hi>Muſculus;</hi> others <hi>ad menſuram quatuor digitorum,</hi> or <hi>palmi minoris longitudinem;</hi> the breadth of foure fingers, or ſmall inches; ſo <hi>Pagnine,</hi> and <hi>Tigurina;</hi> and neere theſe, <hi>Iunius</hi> and <hi>Mollerus palmares poſuiſti dies</hi> thou haſt made my dayes as a hand-breath. The word of the <hi>Septuagint,</hi> is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which the <hi>vulgar Latine</hi> read's <hi>menſurabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les;</hi> and <hi>Hierome,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vide Muſculum in Pſal <hi>39.6.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Breues</hi> ſomething that is meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and therefore, ſhort. For, though the age of <hi>man,</hi> in holy writt, weare's ſometimes the attribute of <hi>dayes;</hi> ſometimes, of <hi>moneths;</hi> ſometimes, of <hi>yeares;</hi> yet theſe dayes, and moneths, and yeares are not without their fraile <hi>Epithets</hi> of, <hi>vani,</hi> or, <hi>breues,</hi> or the like; ſo <hi>Iob</hi> is ſaid <hi>to poſſeſſe many moneths;</hi> but they are <hi>menſes vanitatis, moneths of vanitie, Iob.</hi> 7.2. &amp; not only moneths, but yeares alſo;
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18696:9"/>but theſe years are <hi>anni panciſsimi;</hi> or <hi>breues anni, few yeares, and ſhort Iob.</hi> 16.12. Howeuer, ſuppoſe theſe yeares were multiplied, and lengthned ſomewhat in their <hi>ſpan,</hi> yet they are ſhort ſtill, becauſe numbred.<note place="margin">Pineda in Iob <hi>16.22.</hi>
                  </note> And therefore the Latine verſion here, <hi>breues annos,</hi> the <hi>Hebrew</hi> reads <hi>annos numerari;</hi> and the <hi>Septuagint, annos dinumeratos,</hi> yeares to be numbred, or yeares already numbred, and not only numbred, but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fixt; and not prefixt barely, but circumſcrib'd; circumſcrib'd by the finger of the <hi>Almightie;</hi> and that in a narrow circuite, this <hi>ſpan-long;</hi> ſo <hi>Iob</hi> ſay's, <hi>man's dayes are determined, and his moneths are with thee; thou haſt appointed his bounds that hee cannot paſſe, Iob</hi> 14.5. Inſomuch that dayes,<note place="margin">Bolducus in cap. <hi>16.</hi> Iob. v. <hi>23.</hi> Pined. ibid.</note> or moneths determined are but ſhort; and ſhort dayes and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neths, the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> call <hi>dies numeri,</hi> and <hi>menſes nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meri;</hi> dayes, and moneths of number <hi>quia pauci, &amp; numerabiles</hi> (ſaith <hi>Pineda</hi>) becauſe they are nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, and therefore few. Neither are <hi>dayes</hi> only, and <hi>moneths,</hi> and <hi>yeares</hi> ſo ſtil'd, but the <hi>men</hi> of thoſe <hi>dayes,</hi> and <hi>moneths,</hi> and <hi>yeares;</hi> ſo in the twelfth of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ezech.</hi> 12. <hi>v.</hi> 16, 17.</note> the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſpeaking of the deſolation of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> ſayes, that <hi>God will ſcatter them amongst the Nations, and diſperſe them in their Countrey, but would leaue of them homines paucos à gladio, &amp; à fame,</hi> ſome few of them, that is, <hi>homines numeri,</hi> ſome few that hee had ſelected and numbred, theſe he would reſerue from the ſword, the peſtilence and the famine, that they might declare all their abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations amongſt the <hi>Heathens,</hi> whether they came, that they might know that hee is the Lord their God.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:18696:10"/>
               <p>Thus, meaſure, or number, of times, or ſeaſons, in what proportion ſoeuer, preſuppoſe a kinde of rottenneſſe and inſtabilitie; ſo our <hi>moneths</hi> are num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred, and our dayes meaſur'd,<note place="margin">Pineda in cap. <hi>14.</hi> Iob. v. <hi>5.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Iob</hi> 14.5. that is, <hi>ſhort.</hi> The Latine word there, is <hi>praeciſi,</hi> (according to <hi>Tremeluis</hi>) <hi>decurtati,</hi> others; curtail'd and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; from the originall, <hi>Charats;</hi> which ſignitieth, <hi>acuere,</hi> or, <hi>praeſcindere;</hi> to ſharpen, or cut off. So, the loſtie Prophet, aſſuring to a remnant of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> their ſafctie form the <hi>Aſsirians,</hi> tell's them of a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummatio praeciſa,</hi> in the mid'ſt of the Land. A con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption <hi>decreed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 10.22.</note> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> ſaye's, but that ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring is to narrow, and will not beare vp with the latitude of the originall, and therefore not, a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption; for, that linger's too much; but rather, a conſummation; a preciſe one; ſuch a one as ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues both a certaintie, and quickneſſe in the doing; ſo quicke and certaine, as if it were done, 'ere it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan; and, acted, as ſoone as propheſied; ſo <hi>Ioel</hi> alſo call's the valley of <hi>Iehoſophat,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pin. in cap. <hi>4.</hi> Iob.</note> 
                  <hi>vallis conciſionis;</hi> mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes, multitudes in the valley of conciſion; that is, <hi>vallis abreuiationis;</hi> or, <hi>vallis praeciſionis;</hi> the val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of abreuiation, or cutting off; becauſe that the vaſt multitude of people there met, ſhould bee rari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi'd, and leſſen'd;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioel</hi> 3.14.</note> and only a few number of the Iuſt ſelected. In like ſort, the dayes of <hi>man,</hi> here, may be called <hi>dies conciſionis,</hi> or <hi>dies praeciſi,</hi> becauſe they are abreuiated maimed, cut off, determined, &amp; ſtraight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to a preſcript time; a ſtrict meaſure; this <hi>ſpan-long,</hi> which man can neither diminiſh, nor dilate in his owne power; but hee is pent vp, here, in his nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Royaltie; his fraile incloſure, where his dayes
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:18696:10"/>are ſpanned out, his pillars pitch't; his <hi>non vltra</hi> li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited; his circuits bounded; <hi>&amp; tu poſuiſti terminos,</hi> and thou (O God) haſt appointed thoſe bounds, <hi>&amp; tu poſuiſti dies,</hi> and thou haſt made thoſe dayes; ſo made them, that thou haſt meaſured them; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured them, exactly; by a <hi>ſpan;</hi> a narrow ſpan, which he ſhall neither fall ſhort of, nor exceed, no not one tittle or <hi>punctum</hi> of it; not the breadth of the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt haire, or <hi>atome;</hi> no, not the rare-ſpun <hi>gothſimere;</hi> or any other extenuated or imaginarie thinneſſe whatſoeuer. For <hi>tu conſtituiſti,</hi> and, <hi>tu poſuiſti,</hi> thou haſt appointed, and thou haſt made it ſo:<note place="margin">Iob. <hi>14.5.</hi> Pſal <hi>33.</hi> 6</note> and what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer is thy appointment, is thy Law; a Law not to be corrupted, or minced, or diſanull'd, either by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiuocation, or partialitie, or rigour, or any other iuggling or impoſture of fleſh and bloud. <hi>There is none</hi> (ſaith <hi>Iob</hi>) <hi>that can deliuer out of thy hand. Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuta eius feciſti, &amp; non praeteribit,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob <hi>10.7.</hi> Lat. Interp. in <hi>10.</hi> cap. Iob. v. <hi>20.21.</hi> Prou. <hi>8.</hi> v. <hi>24.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>thou haſt appointed man his bounds that he cannot paſſe,</hi> ſtatutes which he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not violate certain chanels &amp; banks in thy decrees, which he cannot poſſibly exceed. <hi>And as thou haſt eſtabliſhed the clouds, and ſtrengthned the fountaines of the deepe, bound vp the flouds from ouerflowing, and giuen them thy command that they ſhall not paſſe, but placed the ſand as a wall about them by a perpetuall Decree; and though the waues thereof toſſ themſelues,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ier.</hi> 5.22.</note> 
                  <hi>yet can they not preuaile, though they roare, yet can they not ſwell ouer;</hi> ſo all thoſe toſſing; and ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings of fleſh and bloud the ſurges and billowes ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing in the tempeſts of our life,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 38.10, 11.</note> haue their cliffes and ſhoares, &amp; ſtrict limits, and God hath done to them, as to the great deepe, brake vp for them his decreed place, and ſet barres and doores, and ſaid, hither you
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:18696:11"/>ſhall come, no further; here ſhall your proud waues ſtay: for <hi>tu poſuiſti dies,</hi> thou haſt made our dayes, and thoſe dayes but a ſpan-long <hi>&amp; tu conſtituiſti ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minos,</hi> thou haſt appointed our bounds, and thoſe bounds wee ſhall not paſſe.<note place="margin">Pineda in cap. <hi>14.</hi> Iob.</note> And therefore the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted man ſeeme's to complaine of the Almightie, that hee had inuironed him, <hi>terminis ſuis,</hi> with his bounds; that is, <hi>praeceptis ſuo, &amp; ſtatutis,</hi> with his precepts, and his ſtatute; ſuch orecep saud ſtatutes, as he cannot abrogate; ſo in the eight of the <hi>Prouerbs</hi> 29. the Wiſeman ſpeaking of the mightie prouidence of God in ruling and ordering the vaſt deepe, ſayes <hi>Iegem ponebat aquis,</hi> hee gaue the waters a law, or a decree, that they ſhould not paſſe his command, and yet the <hi>ſinger</hi> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> call's this very <hi>law,</hi> a <hi>bound, thou haſt ſet a bound that they cannot paſſe, Pſal.</hi> 104 9 ſo that, that <hi>terminus,</hi> or <hi>bound</hi> was a <hi>law</hi> to them; and this <hi>lex,</hi> or <hi>decree, a bound</hi> to vs; and neither this <hi>bound,</hi> nor <hi>law,</hi> to be ouer-paſt; and therefore we find it once againe ſpoken of in the 148. Pſalme, and there is a <hi>non praeteribit,</hi> to it; it ſhall not paſſe away, paſſe away? No, not one iot, or tittle of it. <hi>Heauen and earth ſhall firſt paſſe away, before one iot or tittle, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Gods Word or Law,</hi> his <hi>poſuit,</hi> or his <hi>conſtituit,</hi> his bound, or his ſpan-long, which are a <hi>law</hi> to him; a law irreuocable, both in matters of life, and death. And therefore this neceſſitie of fate, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth, by the name of a <hi>law,</hi> with a <hi>ſtatutum eſt,</hi> and a <hi>ſemel ſtatutum eſt,</hi> it is <hi>appointed</hi> to <hi>man</hi> to die, and it is <hi>once</hi> appointed. <hi>Statutum eſt</hi> there is the <hi>law,</hi> or the <hi>decree,</hi> and the <hi>ſemel once,</hi> ſayes, that this law is firme, conſtant, inviolable; for God ſpeake's
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:18696:11"/>once, and he ſpeake's but once,<note place="margin">Pinedain cap. Iob.</note> 
                  <hi>vt iterato pracepto opus non ſit,</hi> ſaith <hi>Pineda,</hi> that we ſhould not expect any iteration or doubling of his command. And therefore in the ſeuenteenth of the <hi>Acts,</hi> we haue, though not this <hi>ſtatutum eſt,</hi> the law punctually ſet downe, yet wee haue the <hi>ſtatuta tempora,</hi> the times prefixt for the execution of that law; ſo the text, God hath made of one bloud all the nations of men, and hath <hi>determined the times</hi> before appointed and the bounds of their habitation, <hi>which they cannot paſſe,</hi> the ſix and twentieth verſe of that Chapter. And leaſt we ſhould thinke times determined to be no <hi>law,</hi> our death, which is a thing <hi>determined,</hi> and to a time determined, is call'd, a Teſtament, or, a Law. Remember that death will not bee long, in comming, and that the <hi>Couenant</hi> or <hi>Law</hi> of the graue, is not ſhewed vnto thee. <hi>Ecclus</hi> 14.12.</p>
               <p>So that this buſineſſe of death and the graue, is a law certaine, and prefixt, both for the time and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and that beyond all poſſibilitie of alteration; and therefore whether we ſtile it a <hi>decree,</hi> or a <hi>ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute,</hi> or a <hi>law,</hi> or a <hi>teſtament,</hi> or a <hi>bound,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pin. ibid.</note> or this <hi>ſpan-long, Semper dicis aliquid quod praeteriri non pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> ſayes the <hi>Ieſuite,</hi> there is ſomething inuolu'd that is both conſtant and inuiolable; whoſe ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piers, and walls, and bulwarkes, thou ſhalt neuer ſcale nor digge through; for 'tis the <hi>Almighties Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tadell</hi> and ſtrong fort, ſo garriſon'd and intrencht by his eternall power, and wiſdome; the doores and gates of it ſo barrocade'd, and blockt-vp againſt all inuaſions of <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>bloud,</hi> that no earthly ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem, no temporall aſſault, no humane policie,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18696:12"/>ſhall euer raze or demoliſh; but it ſtand's vnſhooke, againſt all tempeſts; firme, againſt all batteries; ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid, againſt all vnderminings; ſo that if the flouds riſe, and the windes blow, and the waues beat, they ſhall neuer ſtagger it.</p>
               <p>Seeing then there is a <hi>Statutum eſt</hi> paſt vpon all <hi>mankinde,</hi> that it muſt once die (and that ſtatute is not rough, though it be ſometimes vnpleaſing, to die once, ſo wee die no more, for a double death is our due, though not our pay) and knowing that there are preciſe bounds, and limits, <hi>and ſpan-longs to fleſh and bloud,</hi> beyond which it cannot paſſe, and theſe bounds, and ſpans, and limits haue the Inſcription of Gods vnalterable Decree, with the authoritie of his ſtampe and ſeale, his <hi>poſuit,</hi> and his <hi>conſtituit,</hi> let vs take vp the prayer here of our <hi>Pſalmiſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. <hi>38.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Lord make me to know mine end, and the number of my dayes, what it is;</hi> the number, what it is? <hi>&amp; eſt, &amp; non eſt,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>meaſure</hi> of our dayes you haue had in an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act proportion, in this <hi>ſpan-long;</hi> but the number of them,<note place="margin">Aug ibid.</note> is both ſecret, and vncertaine: <hi>it is and it is not,</hi> truly. <hi>Nec eſſe poſſumus dicere, quod nòn ſtat, nèc nòn eſſe, quod venit, &amp; tranſit,</hi> ſaye's the father, <hi>we cannot properly ſay</hi> that that is which remaynes not, nor that is not, which comes and goes. <hi>Dayes paſt,</hi> and <hi>future,</hi> are as no dayes. <hi>Yeſterday,</hi> was; and to <hi>morrow,</hi> will be; and ſo, now, <hi>are not;</hi> and of ſuch things as are not, there is no <hi>number, to-day,</hi> only, is man's; and this not long his, neither; for it is <hi>going;</hi> or if it did not goe, it is but <hi>one day,</hi> and of that, there is <hi>no number,</hi> neither; ſo that the <hi>totall</hi> here,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18696:12"/>
                  <hi>aut nòn est, aut quaſi eſt,</hi> is either no number at all, or,<note place="margin">Aug. vt ſupra.</note> 
                  <hi>as it were,</hi> a number. Summe vp all the minutes and houres thou canſt, and thoſe, truly, and thine owne; thou ſhalt make vp but <hi>one day,</hi> and that day <hi>(wholly)</hi> not thine owne neither. Let's begin from the firſt dawne, or houre of it; where is that houre, ſaith the father? 'tis gone, where is the ſecond then? perchance thou wilt ſay that's gone too; but, the third (doubtleſſe) thou enioy'ſt; that's thine owne;<note place="margin">Aug. ibid.</note> be it ſo; and yet <hi>ſi tertiam dabis, non diem, ſed horam dabis.</hi> Doeſt thou talke then of <hi>number,</hi> that haſt but <hi>a day,</hi> or of a <hi>day,</hi> that haſt but <hi>one houre?</hi> an houre? not that neither, not that <hi>very houre</hi> thou think'ſt thou <hi>enioy'ſt;</hi> for, if ſome part of it bee now paſt, and another as yet remayning; and of that which is paſt thou can'ſt not diſpoſe, becauſe it is not now; nor, of that which remaynes, becauſe it is not yet, what canſt thou giue of this houre? or if thou giueſt, what i'ſt of thine owne thou giueſt? the Father is at a ſtand, here; and in ſteed of a <hi>reſolution</hi> put's a <hi>quaere. Cui committam hoc verbum, vt dicam, Eſt?</hi> what ſhall I doe with the word. <hi>Eſt</hi> (ſaith hee?) 'tis but <hi>one ſyllable,</hi> and <hi>one moment,</hi> and <hi>three letters</hi> in that ſyllable, and moment. Wee cannot come to the <hi>ſecond,</hi> but by the <hi>firſt,</hi> nor to the <hi>third,</hi> but by the <hi>ſecond;</hi> and then <hi>quid mihi de hac vna ſyllaba da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis? &amp; tenes dies, qui vnam ſyllabam non tenes?</hi> doe we talke of <hi>yeares,</hi> and <hi>moneths,</hi> and <hi>dayes,</hi> and <hi>houres,</hi> when wee cannot giue an account of one <hi>ſyllable?</hi> not of <hi>one letter</hi> of it? Away then with this vaine credulitie, this fond aſſurance of our ſetled planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion here below; <hi>momentis tranſuolantibus cuncta
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:18696:13"/>rapiuntur,</hi> all things are ſnatcht away in moments; moments that haue wings, and no ſeete; <hi>momentis tranſuolantibus, moments</hi> that flie away, as if they were affraid of mortality, or loath to aſſiſt it. And yet, behold, our <hi>tents</hi> here are not ſo thinnly built, but they will endure the blaſts (or breathings ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) of a few <hi>dayes,</hi> a few dayes (indeed) that are <hi>ſpann'd-out;</hi> and when theſe are gone, Lord, what are we? ſurely, euen <hi>as nothing;</hi> as nothing <hi>before thee:</hi> ſo the <hi>Prophet</hi> in the words following <hi>Mine Age is as nothing before thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Mine Age is as nothing before thee.</head>
               <q>Mine Age, &amp;c.</q>
               <p>
                  <hi>IVſtinian</hi> reads it <hi>vitamea;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pars ſecunda. auum meum. vulg. lat: Jun. &amp; Trem. Muſc. in Pſal. <hi>39. Aynſworth.</hi> in Pſal. <hi>39. 1. Cor. 7.31.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Pagnine, tempus meum,</hi> my life, and my time; the two Fathers, <hi>Hierome</hi> and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> (following the <hi>Greeke</hi>) <hi>ſubſtantia mea</hi> my ſubſtance; the <hi>Caldee</hi> (not much vnlike) <hi>Corpus meam,</hi> my body; but, the <hi>Hebrew</hi> word, <hi>Cheled,</hi> ſignifies, the <hi>World, Pſal.</hi> 17.14. vſed here, for mans <hi>life</hi> or <hi>Age,</hi> or <hi>time</hi> in the world; ſo that, as the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of this greater world paſſeth away, ſaith the Apoſtle, ſo doth the body and ſubſtance of the <hi>leſſer;</hi> inſomuch that this whole pilgrimage on earth, is but <hi>as nothing</hi> (moſt tranſlations reading here <hi>vt nihil,</hi> or <hi>tanquam nihil</hi>) and though ſome bee ſo mercifull in their rendrings,<note place="margin">Aeuum meum eoram te eſt, ac ſinon eſſot. <hi>Muſc.</hi> Aeuum meum ac ſi nibil eſſet ante te, <hi>Molcrus.</hi>
                  </note> as to make mans <hi>Age</hi> a <hi>ſomething,</hi> yet that hath but an <hi>Eſt, acſi non eſſet:</hi> or els an <hi>Ac,</hi> with a <hi>ſi nibil eſſet:</hi> ſo that I finde little difference in the readings, the one making mans age <hi>as nothing;</hi> the other, a <hi>ſomething,</hi> as if it were not. But ſuppoſe it were a <hi>ſomething,</hi> indeed, ſuch an age
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18696:13"/>as had a ſtabilitie both of <hi>dayes</hi> and <hi>yeeres,</hi> and theſe not <hi>ſpann'd</hi> ſo narrowly, but they might climbe vp to the miracle of a thouſand yeeres, yet this huge maſſe of time is little better then the <hi>tanquam nihil</hi> in the Text, <hi>as nothing before thee,</hi> ſuch a <hi>nothing,</hi> as is reſembled to the decurſion and ſticklenes of <hi>one day,</hi> not <hi>a day preſent,</hi> but already ſpent, <hi>A yeſterday,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.4.</note> 
                  <hi>a yeſterday that is paſt. A thouſand yeeres in thy eyes are but as yeſterday that is paſt,</hi> or as a <hi>wacth</hi> in the night. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.4.</p>
               <p>Had our <hi>Prophet</hi> reſembled it to a <hi>day,</hi> ſuch a day as we enioy; <hi>this day,</hi> or, one houre of this day; or one minute of this houre; or, one moment, or <hi>ictus</hi> of that minute, wee might haue preſuppoſed ſome ſtabilitie, though ſhort-breathd, and panting, in the courſe of <hi>mans</hi> age; but, to <hi>a day,</hi> a day languiſh't, and conſum'd; to <hi>yeſterday,</hi> to yeſterday <hi>expird;</hi> how doth it whiſper our frailty? how our tranſitorineſſe? not ſuch a frailtie, and tranſitorineſſe, as ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after fade and wither, but a rotten tranſitorineſſe, a putriſied frailty; a <hi>yeſterdayes</hi> frailtie and tranſito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe; a <hi>yeſterday</hi> that is worme-eaten and duſtie; a yeſterday <hi>that is paſt.</hi> The naturall man then look't not home to the brittleneſſe of our conſtitution, when he ſtyl'd Man <hi>a creature of a day;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Ariſt. Iob. <hi>8.9.</hi>
                  </note> nor the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man, when hee cloathed him with an <hi>heſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni ſumus,</hi> we are but as <hi>yester day, Iob</hi> 8.9. but, the man after Gods owne heart (whoſe knowledge was as pure as his integritie) he diſplayes him at the full, when he makes his <hi>Age, a ſeaſon obſolete;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.4.</note> 
                  <hi>a Calender</hi> out of date; a yeſterday <hi>that</hi> is paſt.</p>
               <p>And therefore in a deepe contemplation of our
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:18696:14"/>mortalitie (bottoming and ſounding (as it were) all humane wretchedneſſe) hee opens the fleetneſſe of his age by a <hi>nihil,</hi> here, a <hi>nihil</hi> (I confeſſe) with a <hi>tanquam</hi> to it, <hi>Mine Age is as nothing before thee:</hi> as <hi>nothing</hi> (indeed) <hi>before thee;</hi> thy <hi>Omnipotencie,</hi> thy <hi>Infiniteneſſe;</hi> before theſe, <hi>as nothing.</hi> For, if <hi>a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeeres</hi> to thee bee but as <hi>yester day,</hi> muſt bee nothing to thy <hi>thouſand;</hi> thy thouſand thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands; thy myriades of thouſands, thy eternitie; thy euerlaſtingneſſe. And therefore, my <hi>Age,</hi> or, my <hi>ſubstance,</hi> is a <hi>tanquam nihil ante te, Ante te, qui vides hoc</hi> (Saint <hi>Augustine eccho's</hi>) <hi>&amp; cum hoc video, ante te video, ante te homines non video.</hi> I confeſſe, that it is nothing that <hi>I am,</hi> in reſpect of him; that <hi>is, ante te domine, ante te; vbi oculi tui ſunt, non vbi oculi hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mani ſunt;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal.</note> ſo the <hi>Father</hi> warble's. To a blemiſht or a deluded eye (and ſuch a one is a mortall eye) my age may be ſomething; <hi>a ſomething</hi> of ſome few dimenſions, <hi>a ſpan-long,</hi> and yet this is but a <hi>tanquam nihil,</hi> a <hi>tanquam nihil,</hi> vnto <hi>man,</hi> too; <hi>as nothing</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him: but to thee; to thy eyes (which are brigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then thoſe beames, which dazzle mine) thoſe eyes, <hi>ſubstantia mea, purè nihil;</hi> no <hi>tanquam,</hi> there; mine age is nothing; purely nothing, there. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? why? <hi>vniuerſa vanitas omnis homo,</hi> euery man is <hi>vanity;</hi> ſuch a vanity as is ſtol'n-by; or els, now going; as, <hi>yester day;</hi> or, as a <hi>watch</hi> in the night. And, theſe haue their <hi>tanquam nihil,</hi> too; are as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing before thee; ſo truly nothing, that they make not vp an <hi>Age,</hi> or a <hi>day,</hi> but ſome few <hi>houres;</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make vp the watch of a night; no more.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18696:14"/>But ſuppoſe this <hi>tanquam nihil</hi> beaten out to the perfection of an <hi>Age;</hi> and that age, <hi>threeſcore and teu:</hi> this, trodden on to an hundred; that trebled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vp to <hi>Nestors;</hi> and his, to <hi>Methuſalah's;</hi> yet all theſe would not make vp our number of <hi>a thouſand;</hi> and ſo, in God's eyes, would be leſſe then a <hi>day;</hi> then a <hi>day</hi> that is paſt. Than a <hi>day?</hi> one night; nay, one poore watch in that night; a <hi>watch</hi> of ſome three houres-ſpace, that's all. For the <hi>Iewes</hi> deuided their <hi>day</hi> into twelue houres, and ſubdiuided their night into foure <hi>watches,</hi> and euery watch, three houres.<note place="margin">1. Euening. 2. Midnight. 3. Cock-crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 4. Dawne. <hi>Mare.</hi> 13.35. <hi>Math.</hi> 14.13.</note> A goodly <hi>monarchhie,</hi> of <hi>fleſh</hi> and <hi>bloud; a ſpacious; ſouerainty</hi> (no doubt) both in <hi>power</hi> and <hi>time;</hi> a <hi>Reigne</hi> of ſome three houres; three houres of a <hi>night</hi> too, not of a <hi>day;</hi> as though the time of our ſway, and ſcepter, here, were attended meerely with ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity and dulneſſe, a <hi>ſceane</hi> of heauineſſe and <hi>ſlum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> ſuch as are incident to this <hi>watch in the night.</hi> And, indeed, what is our life, but a very <hi>Watch?</hi> and the the time of it, but as the night ſeaſon? wherein, by reaſon of the <hi>darkeneſſe</hi> that mantles, and o're<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpreads it, wee grope in vncertenties and errours: the light wee haue of things is but weake and bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed; a glimmering, or twinkling onely, no true light; and, rather a conceipt, and apprehenſion of what wee <hi>ſeeme</hi> to ſee, then an exactken or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of what wee <hi>ſhould.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Moreouer, in this <hi>watch</hi> of ours, wee are apt to nod, and forget; forget, not onely that we are here at <hi>Sentinell;</hi> who ſet vs here; and the ſhort time wee are at it, <hi>our three boures;</hi> but the ſtrict charge of our <hi>Commander,</hi> and the danger of ſurprizall and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:18696:15"/>defeat, by the inuaſion of our powerfull <hi>Aduerſary.</hi> But, <hi>night</hi> and <hi>frailtie</hi> (as what is our <hi>age</hi> but theſe?) are beauie-ey'd, and drowzie; and then, our <hi>three houres,</hi> are (perchance) no more a <hi>watch,</hi> but <hi>a dreame;</hi> And what is our age but a dreame too? a dreame of ſome <hi>three houres;</hi> and that's a long one (you will ſay) but, howeuer long, 'tis but a dreame; and, as a dreame, not long neither. But did I ſay, mans <hi>Age</hi> was a <hi>dreame?</hi> nay, rather, <hi>man,</hi> in that <hi>Age,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tob</hi> 20.8.</note> 
                  <hi>a dreame. Hee flieth away,</hi> as a <hi>dreame,</hi> and is chaſed as a <hi>viſion in the night. Iob.</hi> 20.8. So that, now, here is a <hi>dreame</hi> in a <hi>dreame,</hi> Ezechiels <hi>viſion; a wheele in a wheele,</hi> this turne's in that, and yet, but one <hi>vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> one <hi>dreame;</hi> or, if there be diſparitie any where, 'tis <hi>in man;</hi> and he, the vainer <hi>dreame</hi> of the two.</p>
               <p>Our life (you know) hath beene call'd a <hi>ſhadow;</hi> and not only a <hi>ſhadow,</hi> but a <hi>vaine ſhadow,</hi> in which man is ſaid to walke; <hi>He walketh in a vaine ſhadow,</hi> in the ſeuenth verſe of this <hi>Pſalme;</hi> And not only <hi>walke's</hi> in it, but <hi>dreame's</hi> in it; ſo dreame's <hi>in it,</hi> that he is <hi>of it,</hi> too; and therefore the Heathen call's him <hi>vmbrae ſomnium,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Pindar.</note> the dreame of a ſhadow; and what is that, but the <hi>ſhadow</hi> of a <hi>ſhadow?</hi> for there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo truly a <hi>ſhadow,</hi> as a <hi>dreame,</hi> in which (often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times) there are ſtrange obiects preſented to the <hi>phantaſie,</hi> whereof in <hi>nature,</hi> and true <hi>being,</hi> there is not ſo much, as a <hi>reſemblance,</hi> no, not a <hi>ſhadow;</hi> and yet, euen theſe ſo captiue and ſhackle the whole man, that (according to the varietie of <hi>ſpecies</hi> offered) they take vs, either with delight, or horror; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times commanding our ſigh, our groane, our teare; ſometime, our eleuation of ſpirits; our applauſe, our
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:18696:15"/>laughter; euen then, when our out ward ſenſes ſeeme fetter'd and chain'd-vp in the bands of ſleepe; and all this was but the <hi>Fiſher-man's</hi> dreame in <hi>Theoeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> whoſe <hi>Golden Bootie</hi> vaniſht with his <hi>dreame,</hi> and hee awak's at length to himſelfe, and his olde wants gull'd with <hi>an apparition</hi> and <hi>ſhadow</hi> of that ſubſtance, of which he now find's there was neither <hi>ſhadow,</hi> nor <hi>ſubſtance,</hi> truly, but, a <hi>dreame</hi> of both.</p>
               <p>Againe, <hi>Dreames</hi> are the true <hi>Hieroglyphicks</hi> of our mortall ſtate, in which the whole paſſages of our life, are either propheſied, or acted; and that, much to the complexion, or qualitie of humours in him that dreameth. Sometimes, they are <hi>ambitious;</hi> and then we thinke we are vpon the tops of <hi>hils,</hi> or <hi>mountaines;</hi> now on <hi>Baſan,</hi> then, on <hi>Libanus;</hi> where (for our pride and loftineſſe) wee are called <hi>Oakes,</hi> and <hi>Cedars;</hi> ſometimes they are more <hi>humble,</hi> and deiected, and then wee grouell <hi>in bottomes, and in vallies;</hi> where, for our low eſtate, wee are call'd <hi>ſhrubs</hi> and <hi>hyſop;</hi> ſometimes they are <hi>preſumptuous,</hi> and then we are at the fall of a <hi>ſteepe Cliffe,</hi> or <hi>Rocke;</hi> ſometimes, they are <hi>deſperate,</hi> and then we are at the <hi>quick-ſand,</hi> or the <hi>gulfe;</hi> ſometimes, they are <hi>vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious,</hi> and then we are at the <hi>battlement,</hi> or <hi>pinna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> of the Temple; ſometimes they are <hi>puſillanimous</hi> and fearefull; and then we are at the <hi>roaring, or ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing</hi> of the great deepe; ſometimes they inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate a kinde of <hi>auſpice</hi> and bleſt abundance, and then we tumble in <hi>Arabian</hi> ſpices, gold of <hi>Ophir, Indian Diamonds;</hi> but this (for the moſt part) is a <hi>very dreame,</hi> ſuch a one, as our <hi>phantaſie</hi> tell's vs, in our <hi>dreame,</hi> is a <hi>dreame indeed;</hi> ſometimes againe, they
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18696:16"/>are <hi>Ominous,</hi> and then ghaſtly apparitions, and feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſhreekes ſtartle and affright vs; <hi>Galbas halter,</hi> or <hi>knife,</hi> or <hi>poyſon,</hi> or ſome other Engine of bloud and death more horrid; laſtly, ſometimes they are <hi>fatall,</hi> and then we dreame that we haue <hi>feet of clay;</hi> walke in a <hi>Caemeterium,</hi> or a <hi>Golgotha,</hi> tread amongſt tombes, or dead mens bones, ſtumble at a <hi>Coffin,</hi> or (perchance) a <hi>greene medow,</hi> and that (they ſay) is an infallible <hi>praediction of mortalitie;</hi> I know not whether a <hi>medow</hi> be, I am ſure <hi>graſſe,</hi> or a <hi>flower</hi> is; or, if not a <hi>prediction,</hi> at leaſt, an <hi>embleme. All fleſh is graſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 40 6.</note> 
                  <hi>and the beautie thereof as the flower of the field, the graſſe withereth, and the flower fadeth, Eſay</hi> 40.6.</p>
               <p>Marke, the ſubſtance of fleſh and bloud (here) is but <hi>graſſe,</hi> ſuch graſſe as <hi>withereth,</hi> and the <hi>beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> of that ſubſtance, as a flower, ſuch a <hi>flower,</hi> as is open to <hi>all tempeſts, a flower of the field:</hi> and that flower of the field which <hi>fadeth</hi> too. Here is nothing but withering, and fading, no time of <hi>flouriſhing,</hi> as if <hi>man</hi> were a <hi>piece</hi> meerely of <hi>declination,</hi> and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted before he <hi>grew.</hi> And yet loe, he <hi>groweth,</hi> and he <hi>flouriſheth</hi> too, but it is for a <hi>day only;</hi> a day? nay. the firſt part of that day, the <hi>morning;</hi> ſo ſayes our Pſalmiſt.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 90.6.</note> 
                  <hi>In the morning be flouriſheth, and groweth vp, Pſal.</hi> 90.6. That's well; here is <hi>man,</hi> and the <hi>glory of man;</hi> he <hi>groweth,</hi> and he <hi>flouriſheth;</hi> and all this is in the <hi>morning;</hi> But what followes this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and this growth, and this flouriſhing? ſurely, a <hi>ripeneſſe,</hi> a <hi>ſickle,</hi> and a <hi>harueſt;</hi> an <hi>euening,</hi> a <hi>cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting-downe,</hi> and a <hi>withering.</hi> In the <hi>euening</hi> he is cut downe, and <hi>withereth,</hi> the ſame verſe, of the ſame <hi>Pſalme.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:18696:16"/>
               <p>But, hath all <hi>ſleſh and bloud</hi> (the graſſe here men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned) a time of <hi>growing vp</hi> 'ere it be <hi>cut downe?</hi> a <hi>flouriſhing</hi> before it <hi>wither's?</hi> wee reade of graſſe, that wither's before it growes; before it growes vp, vp to any ripeneſſe, or perfection; and this the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt call's <hi>graſſe on the houſe top, Pſal.</hi> 129.6, 7.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.6, 7.</note> So thinly growne, that the <hi>mower, filleth not his hand, nor he that bindeth vp fheaues, his boſome.</hi> Oh, that the <hi>Top of a houſe,</hi> the maine <hi>beame,</hi> and <hi>rafters</hi> of a <hi>Family,</hi> the chiefe <hi>buttreſſe,</hi> and pillar of a <hi>name,</hi> ſhould bee ſo barren, the fruit of it ſo ſoone fade, when thoſe that are nearer earth, take better roote. But loe; <hi>Hee grew ſo thinly vp,</hi> that there is not ſo much left of him, as to <hi>fill a hand,</hi> not to make vp this <hi>ſpan-long,</hi> in the text, no not this <hi>tanquam nibil;</hi> He withered before he grew-vp; wee had him only in the <hi>morning,</hi> in the blooming of youth, when the <hi>Damaske</hi> and the <hi>Lilly</hi> daunc'd in the cheeke: Before his <hi>noone,</hi> he is reapt away, and his ſheafe <hi>bound-vp,</hi> and now he is gone, gone like the <hi>day</hi> you heard of, the <hi>yeſterday,</hi> or the <hi>watch,</hi> or the <hi>ſhadow,</hi> or the <hi>dreame,</hi> or the <hi>graſſe,</hi> or the fraile <hi>flower,</hi> nothing remayning, but the memory, that <hi>Hee was;</hi> And why? <hi>Vniuerſa vanitas omnis home;</hi> ſurely, <hi>man</hi> is <hi>vanitie; euerie man is vanitie;</hi> euery <hi>man, in his beſt ſtate is vanitie;</hi> euery man, in his beſt ſtate, is <hi>alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether</hi> vanitie. So the words runne in the next part. Euery man in his beſt ſtate is <hi>altogether vanitie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Euerie man in his,<note place="margin">Parstertia.</note> &amp;c.</head>
               <p>THe tranſlations (here) runne diuerſly; ſo doe the faucies on them. <hi>Vniuerſa vanitas omnis
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:18696:17"/>homo;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. Muſculus. Mollerus. Iun. Trem. in locuin.</note> ſo, Saint <hi>Auguſtine; omnis vanitas vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus homo;</hi> ſo <hi>Muſculus; mera vanitas omnis homo;</hi> ſo <hi>Mollerus;</hi> and <hi>omnimoda vanitas omnis homo;</hi> ſo, <hi>Iunius</hi> and <hi>Tremelius.</hi> Euery Tranſlation is dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-ſtrung, and harp's altogether on the plurall. The Prophet ſayes not, <hi>I am vaine,</hi> or <hi>man is vaine,</hi> or, <hi>man is vanitie;</hi> nor that men are vaine, or <hi>vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie;</hi> but the whole <hi>ſeries,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aynſworth in Pſal. <hi>39.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>deſcent</hi> come within the <hi>chorus; Euerie man is vanitie;</hi> nay, <hi>euery man</hi> is <hi>euerie vanitie; all mankind, all manner of vanitie;</hi> ſo the Root, <hi>All</hi> Adam, <hi>all Hebeb, all mankind, all vanitie.</hi> There is nothing within the round of this little <hi>world,</hi> the <hi>whole circuit of fleſh and bloud,</hi> (who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, whatſoeuer, or how great ſoeuer) but it is <hi>vaine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bolduc. in cap. <hi>11.</hi> Ioh. v. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>vanitie, all vanitie.</hi> And therefore ſome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentators (peruſing that of the eleuenth of <hi>Iob, verſ.</hi> 11. <hi>God knoweth vaine man</hi>) reade it <hi>nouit Deus ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum vanitatem,</hi> God knoweth the vanitie of men: or, as others, more nimbly, <hi>nouit Deus homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vanitatis;</hi> God knoweth the <hi>men of vanitie.</hi> So, Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> paraphraſing on that of the Preacher, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Vanitie of vanities, all is vanitie.</hi> will not reade the words,<note place="margin">Aug. lib de vera Religione cap. <hi>21.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Vanitas vanitatum,</hi> but <hi>vanitas vanitantium,</hi> as if <hi>men</hi> made the <hi>vanitie,</hi> and not <hi>vanitie</hi> the <hi>men,</hi> ſo. <hi>Ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> fruſtra additum eſt vanitantium,</hi> (ſaith the Father,) <hi>quia ſi vanitantes detrahas, non eritcorpus vanitas, ſed in ſuo genere, quamuis extremam pulchritudinem, ſine vllo errore remonſtrabit,</hi> in his Booke, <hi>de ver a Religione, cap.</hi> 21. And, indeed, we too much iniure and diſparage, not only the times we liue in, but alſo, thoſe of our Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours, crying out on the <hi>vanitie of either,</hi> when
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:18696:17"/>the Stoyicke tels vs, <hi>hominum ſunt ista,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sen. Epiſt. <hi>56.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>non tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum;</hi> the <hi>vanitie</hi> is in the <hi>man,</hi> and not in the <hi>Age;</hi> or, if it were there, and the <hi>vanitie</hi> of all creatures within it, <hi>man</hi> would ingroſſe it all; ſo, the ſame Saint <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> expounding the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Aug. in cap. <hi>8.</hi> Ro. cap. <hi>53.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>vanitati ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecta eſt creatura,</hi> the creature is ſubiect vnto <hi>vanitie, Rom.</hi> 8. Firſt, put's <hi>all vanitie</hi> into the creature, and then; <hi>all creatures into man,</hi> and that without the leaſt <hi>calumnie,</hi> or, <hi>iniuſtice</hi> (ſo he profeſſes) <hi>omnem crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam in ipſo homine, ſine vlla calumnia cogitemus,</hi> in his tract vpon the <hi>Romans, cap.</hi> 13. And, indeed, it was iuſt, that he who had the glory of all creatures, whil'ſt he ſtood cloathed in his <hi>integritie,</hi> ſhould haue all their <hi>frailtie,</hi> too, when hee was diſrob'd; and ſo it fell out at length; that hee that was the occaſion of <hi>all vanitie, man,</hi> was all <hi>vanitie</hi> himſelfe.<note place="margin">Verſe <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> There was a <hi>time,</hi> when he was but <hi>like</hi> vnto it, Man is <hi>like</hi> vnto <hi>vanitie, Pſal.</hi> 144. now <hi>He is vanitie</hi> it ſelfe, 'tis his eſſentiall, and proper qualitie; not in part, or reſemblance only, but, <hi>altogether</hi> vanitie; <hi>man is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vanitie.</hi> And what is that?<note place="margin">Aug. in Pſal. <hi>38.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Totum hoc quod tranſit vanitas dicitur. Euerie tranſitorineſſe is a vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie;</hi> That which reſide's not, we call <hi>vaine,</hi> becauſe it <hi>vaniſheth;</hi> ſo doth a <hi>vapour,</hi> we ſay, or a <hi>ſmoake,</hi> and man is both; and therefore a <hi>vanitie,</hi> and a <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie;</hi> or, (if you pleaſe) once more, a <hi>vanitie</hi> of <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities;</hi> for that which the <hi>Septuagint</hi> read's ſo in their <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; <hi>Hierome,</hi> and others would haue read <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>vapor fumi,</hi> and, <hi>aurea tenuis,</hi> the vapour of a ſmoake, or, a thinne aire; <hi>Hebel, a ſoone vaniſhing vapour,</hi> as the breath of ones mouth, or noſtrils; ſo <hi>Viues</hi> note's vpon the Father, in his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18696:18"/>twentieth, <hi>De Ciuitate Dei, cap.</hi> 3. T'is true then, whatſoeuer <hi>vaniſheth,</hi> we call <hi>vanitie;</hi> and <hi>man,</hi> that <hi>vaniſht vanitie;</hi> inſomuch that hee ſeeme's to bee a fraile <hi>creature,</hi> indeed; ſome what leſſe then <hi>vanitie,</hi> or <hi>beyond</hi> it.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal</hi> 109.23.</note> And therefore our Prophet doth not only compare him to a <hi>ſhadow</hi> (which muſt as a <hi>ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow vaniſh</hi>) but to that <hi>ſhadow,</hi> when it <hi>declineth, Pſal.</hi> 109.23. and it ſeemes this is not enough neither, and therefore,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal</hi> 102.12.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 102.12. <hi>Dies mei ſimiles vmbrae declinatae; I am gone ae a ſhadow declin'd.</hi> He is <hi>gone,</hi> and <hi>declin'd,</hi> not <hi>declining,</hi> as if his paſſage were ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>coniectur'd</hi> then <hi>diſcern'd.</hi> And therefore, in Scripture, we ſeldome finde <hi>man's Age</hi> reſembled to a ſhadow, but there is a <hi>fugit</hi> with it, <hi>fugit velut vm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra. Iob.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 14.12.</note> 14.12. Hee <hi>ſties</hi> as a <hi>ſhadow;</hi> flie's with a nimble wing; ſo nimbly, that ſometimes Hee out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe's the acuteneſſe of our ſight; <hi>I be held him</hi> (ſay's <hi>Dauid</hi>) <hi>and hee was gone,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal</hi> 37.37.</note> 
                  <hi>I ſought him, and hee was no where to be found;</hi> ſo alſo, <hi>dies nostri, quaſi vmbrae ſuper terram,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.15.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; nulla est mora,</hi> 1. <hi>Chron.</hi> 29.15. Our dayes are as a ſhadow vpon earth, and there is no ſtay; they paſſe along; nay, they flie; flie ſo ſwift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they are gone, when we thinke them going, like a gaſping coale, which in one Act, glare's, and dye's; or the rude ſalutations of <hi>fire</hi> and <hi>powder,</hi> which but <hi>meet,</hi> and <hi>part; touch,</hi> and <hi>conſume.</hi> And, indeed (if we but obſerue) a <hi>ſhadow</hi> is not ſo proper a reſemblance of our <hi>life,</hi> as of our <hi>death;</hi> or, rather, ſomething betweene <hi>both. T'is an vnequall mixture of light and darkneſſe;</hi> or rather, a <hi>light</hi> mask't, or <hi>vayl'd-vp in darkneſſe,</hi> ſo that, the greater part muſt be <hi>obſcuritie;</hi> and that reſemble's <hi>death;</hi> what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne's of <hi>light,</hi> is ſcreen'd and intercepted, and ſo
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:18696:18"/>look's but dimly towards life. <hi>Euerie ſhadow</hi> is an <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect night,</hi> and <hi>euery night, a metaphoricall death. Sleepe</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> haue beene long ſince call'd <hi>two ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters;</hi> and <hi>Night,</hi> the mother of them both. Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, as euery ſhadow is <hi>an imperfect night,</hi> ſo euery life is an <hi>imperfect death.</hi> The greater the <hi>ſhadow</hi> is, the nearer vnto night, and ſo is the life protract'd, vnto death. And therefore our Prophet knowing that his earthly Tent was a little <hi>wind-ſhooke,</hi> and obnoxious to daily ruine, wil haue his age emblem'd by a <hi>ſhadow</hi> that is declin'd, <hi>ad occaſum vergens,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>In Pſal.</hi> 102.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 109.23.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; in tenebras euaneſcens,</hi> ſaith <hi>Muſcuius;</hi> haſtning to <hi>darkneſſe,</hi> and the <hi>night,</hi> and that <hi>night, death.</hi> When the Sunne is in the <hi>Meridian,</hi> and the beames of it perpendicular to our bodies, <hi>ſhadowes</hi> change not ſuddenly, but when it begin's to decline to the fall, euery moment, almoſt, they vary; and therefore his dayes are <hi>velut vmbrainclinata, ſeu ſerotina,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Muſeul. ibid.</note> as an euening <hi>ſhadow</hi> which <hi>decline's</hi> with the Sunne, and ſo ſet's. For, though <hi>ſhadowes</hi> appeare larger, when the Sunne is neere the fall, yet that <hi>greatneſſe</hi> is not fatre from <hi>vaniſhing; vanitie</hi> (I ſhould ſay) the <hi>va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie</hi> in the text (here) <hi>man;</hi> whoſe honours and triumphs, at the height, and, in his <hi>best ſtate,</hi> are but as <hi>ſhadowes</hi> at noone; and his dayes, but as <hi>ſhadowes</hi> neere the ſet; nay, not ſo hopefull, for they returne againe with the Sunne; but <hi>man</hi> once ſet, riſeth not, till the Sunne and Heauens ſhall be no more. <hi>Iob.</hi> 14.12. And twere well that only the <hi>time of mans</hi> life were <hi>vanitie,</hi> but his <hi>actions</hi> in that time are a wilder <hi>vanitie</hi> then the other. The Poets ſignified ſo much, when they ſet in combuſtion all <hi>Greece</hi> and <hi>Aſia</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:18696:19"/>for a gaudie <hi>Apple;</hi> and all <hi>Troy</hi> and <hi>Greece,</hi> for a <hi>faire Curtizan;</hi> two daintie trifles to cauſe ſuch bloudie agitations in <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Empires.</hi> What, but <hi>vanitie</hi> could haue proiected it? What but this, <hi>omnimoda vanitas,</hi> put it in execution? But, who knowes not, that moſt things arriue <hi>mankind,</hi> as they ſeeme, not as they are? As wee pleaſe to fancie them, not as they proue in their owne nature? And ſo wee are fool'd out of the <hi>truth,</hi> and <hi>realtie</hi> of things, by a vaine ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of what they are not; ſhewing one thing in the rinde, an externall appearance, another, in the core and internall eſſence; <hi>Sophistications, Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures, Lies.</hi> And therefore the Prophet complaines on the ſonnes of men, that they lou'd <hi>Vanitie,</hi> and followed after <hi>lies, Pſal.</hi> 4.9. not only becauſe all worldly allurements yeeld no true contentation, and felicitie, but becauſe (in very deed) they tend either to equiuocation, or falſhood; a deceiueable falſhood (ſo the word <hi>Cozab</hi> ſignifie's) which is ſuch a <hi>lie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ayneſworth. in Pſal. <hi>4.9.</hi>
                  </note> as deceiue's mens expectations; and therefore that which in the twelfth <hi>Pſalme, verſe</hi> 3. We tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late <hi>deceitfull lips,</hi> according to the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> is <hi>falſe vanitie,</hi> or <hi>vaine falſhood,</hi> the word <hi>Shau</hi> noting both <hi>vanitie</hi> of words, and deeds, and ſometimes that which is falſe too. Here upon the Prophet <hi>Agur</hi> amongſt other petitions he preferr'd to his God, his principall deſire was, that hee would remoue from him, <hi>vanitie</hi> and <hi>lies, Pro.</hi> 30.8. And commonly they go hand in hand; for, whatſoeuer is <hi>vain</hi> muſt be <hi>falſe</hi> too; Inſomuch that vnder the word <hi>vanitie,</hi> a <hi>lie</hi> paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:18696:19"/>ſrequently in <hi>Scripture,</hi> or,<note place="margin">Vide Pineda &amp; Boldnc. in cap. <hi>11.</hi> Iob <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> at leaſt in the <hi>Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> on it: ſo in the eleuenth of <hi>Iob,</hi> what the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar read's, <hi>hominum vanitatem,</hi> vanitie of men, <hi>Pag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nine</hi> call's <hi>homines mendaces,</hi> and <hi>Caietan, homines falſitatis,</hi> lying men, or, men of falſhood;<note place="margin">Pagn. Vatab. Caiet. in cap. <hi>11.</hi> Job. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> and <hi>Vata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blus,</hi> (vnwilling, as it ſeemes, to ſunder <hi>vanitie</hi> from the <hi>lie</hi>) tranſlate's both wayes, <hi>Nouit Deus quàm va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni, &amp; ne quàm homines.</hi> God knoweth how <hi>vaine</hi> and <hi>falſe</hi> men are; And therefore in the 62. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10. the <hi>Latine</hi> hath it, <hi>Mendaces homines in ſtateris,</hi> men are lyes in the ballance; the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> thus, men are <hi>vanitie</hi> in the ballance. And, indeed, the whole race of mankind come's within the verge of theſe two words; if they be of cheape and humble conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they are call'd <hi>Vanitie;</hi> if, of a more climing, high, and noble eſtate, a <hi>lie. Men of low degree are vanitie, and men of high degree are alye, Pſal.</hi> 62.9.<note place="margin">Aynſworth in Pſal. <hi>62.9.</hi>
                  </note> A <hi>lie,</hi> or a <hi>vanitie?</hi> nay, lighter then both; ſo that if they were laid in ballances together, they would <hi>mount vp,</hi> ſayes the text; <hi>In ballances to mount vp, they together are lighter then vanitie;</hi> intimating,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.10.</note> that if <hi>all men</hi> were put together in one ballance, and this <hi>vanitie and lie,</hi> in another, the <hi>ballances would mount vp,</hi> and the <hi>frailtie in mans ſide.</hi> A prettie piece of <hi>aeyre,</hi> and <hi>leuitie,</hi> that <hi>vanitie</hi> ſhould weigh-downe; or, <hi>alie; childhood,</hi> or <hi>wantonneſſe,</hi> or <hi>folly,</hi> or <hi>igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,</hi> are not ſo light; nay, not the <hi>leuitie</hi> of all theſe, <hi>woman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Locuſt,</hi> or the <hi>Graſhopper</hi> (creatures of emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe and feare) are no greater ſlaues of the winde then he. <hi>Hee is toſſed to and froas the Graſhopper, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18696:20"/>driuen away as the Locuſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. Iun. &amp; Trem. Pſal. <hi>30.</hi> In imagine non in vmbra.</note> 
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 109.23. Thus, his whole <hi>life</hi> is but a <hi>toſsing,</hi> or a <hi>driuing</hi> (types of inſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie, and trouble) and theſe in a <hi>vaine</hi> way too; ſo our <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> here; <hi>He walke's in a vaine Image</hi> (as if his life were rather ſuppoſitious, and imaginarie, then a life indeed) and in this, he is at no <hi>peace,</hi> but he <hi>diſquieteth</hi> himſelfe <hi>in vaine,</hi> or, (as ſome read it) in <hi>vanitie</hi> doth hee make a ſtirre; And what is the iſſue of this <hi>vaine tumult? He beapeth vp riches, and knoweth not who ſhall gather them,</hi> in the ſeuenth verſe of this Pſalme. Of all earthly vanities this is the moſt <hi>ſuperlatiue;</hi> the <hi>omuimoda vanitas</hi> in the Text,<note place="margin">Aug. de Temp. <hi>49.</hi> in cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                  </note> is not ſo <hi>vaine</hi> as this. <hi>Conturbaris, ô homo</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) <hi>Vanè conturbaris; quare? the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurizas; cui? neſcis.</hi> A rare prouidence (no doubt) to treaſure vp, I know not what, for I know not whom. The Scripture ſcarce afford's a <hi>fleeting at tribute to fleſh and bloud,</hi> but <hi>Riches</hi> haue a ſhare in it. <hi>Men</hi> are call'd <hi>vanities,</hi> ſo are <hi>Riches, ſhadowes,</hi> ſo are <hi>Riches; nothing,</hi> ſo are <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</hi> Hearke, <hi>Mammoniſt,</hi> here is a <hi>vanitie,</hi> as well of <hi>Riches,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. ibid.</note> as of <hi>men,</hi> and both theſe a <hi>ſhadow,</hi> and <hi>a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> But ſuppoſe thoſe <hi>riches</hi> firme, and ſolid; what then? <hi>Non infructuosè conturbaris, ſed vanè contur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baris,</hi> (ſayes the Father) perchance the trouble is not ſo <hi>fruitleſſe;</hi> but, 'tis as <hi>vaine; vaine?</hi> Why? <hi>Thou knoweſt not who ſhall gather them;</hi> and, if thou knoweſt not that, why doeſt thou <hi>heape them vp?</hi> or, if thou do'ſt, tell me, <hi>for whom?</hi> thy ſelfe? dar'ſt thou ſay ſo, that art to die? thy iſſue, then? dar'ſt thou ſay ſo of thoſe that ſhall? <hi>Magna pietas! the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaurizat
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:18696:20"/>pater filijs; imò, magna vanitas, theſaurizat moriturus, morituris;</hi> the Father, ſtill, in his nine and fortieth Sermon, <hi>de Tompore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But grant thy heapes inlarg'd; thy fortunes, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous; thy loynes, fruitfull, yet there is a <hi>moth</hi> and <hi>gangreene</hi> haunt's that eſtate that is purchaſed with too much <hi>ſolicitude,</hi> the heire of it, (often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time) ſubiect to a fit of <hi>improuidence,</hi> or <hi>luxurie,</hi> or <hi>pride,</hi> or <hi>folly,</hi> or elſe, that common feuer of <hi>luſt,</hi> and <hi>riot;</hi> or (perchance) the <hi>palſie</hi> of a <hi>die,</hi> ſhake's out his poſteritie into miſerie, and want; and then <hi>Ille fluenào perdidit, quod tu laborando congregâſti;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Aug. vt ſupra.</note> what before was a <hi>dropſie,</hi> is now growne to a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption,</hi> thy baſer <hi>auarice,</hi> to a reproachfull <hi>penurie;</hi> and what thou haſt long fed on, with the <hi>bread</hi> of <hi>carefulneſſe,</hi> is at laſt brought to the <hi>bread of ſarrow,</hi> to the <hi>leane cheeke,</hi> the <hi>hollow eyes,</hi> and <hi>the cleane teeth;</hi> and hee that was before the obiect of thy wretchednes, and poore <hi>anxietie,</hi> is now,<note place="margin">He that by v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury and vniuſt gaine increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, he ſhall gather it for him that will pittie the poore. <hi>Prou.</hi> 28.18. <hi>Vide Eccleſ.</hi> 2.26. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.</note> of another mans <hi>Charitie,</hi> and <hi>remorſe;</hi> and then thou wilt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge this <hi>vanè conturbaris,</hi> too, that thou haſt diſquieted thy ſelfe in <hi>vaine,</hi> and to no purpoſe hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped vp riches, ſince thou knoweſt not who hath ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered them. But, ſuppoſe thy iſſue, both hopefull, and prouident, ſuch a one as will not only <hi>preſerue</hi> thy treaſure, but <hi>inhaunce it;</hi> yet oftentimes his <hi>vine is barren,</hi> and there are <hi>no Oliue plants about his table;</hi> God doth ſhut vp the wombe, or ſo emaſculate his loynes, that either the fruit of it is <hi>abortiue,</hi> or none at all; or, if he haue any (as <hi>Bildad</hi> ſaid vnto <hi>Iob</hi>) <hi>the firſt borne of death ſhall deuoure his ſtrength,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 18.13, 14.</note> 
                  <hi>and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18696:21"/>bring him to the King of terrours,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eccleſ <hi>5.4.</hi> Iob <hi>33.34.</hi> Iob <hi>15.33.</hi> Vide Eccleſ <hi>4.8</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>he ſhall ſhake off his vnripe grape as the vine and cast off his flower as the Oliue;</hi> and then the <hi>vanè conturbaris</hi> comes here al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo; <hi>He hath diſquieted himſelfe in vaine, and heaped vp riches, and knowe's not who ſhall gather them.</hi> Thus, Except the Lord build the houſe, they labour but in vaine that build it;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Children are the heritage of the Lord, and the fruit of the wombe is his reward;</hi> others may <hi>plant,</hi> and <hi>water,</hi> but <hi>be giue's the increaſe;</hi> and where he giue's them as bleſſings (as oftentimes he doe's) they are as <hi>arrowes</hi> in the <hi>hand of the ſtrong man,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 127.4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>and happie is hee that hath his quiuer full:</hi> but when they are giuen otherwiſe (as they are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times) as the <hi>whip</hi> and <hi>ſword</hi> of a declining houſe then they are as <hi>arrowes</hi> in <hi>the hand</hi> of the <hi>Almighty; arrowes</hi> that are <hi>ſharpe,</hi> and <hi>keene,</hi> ſhot from a dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hand, and a bow of ſteele; <hi>arrowes</hi> that <hi>ſticke faſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob <hi>7.</hi>
                  </note> and pierce the very <hi>ioynts</hi> and the <hi>marrow; the venome whereof drinketh vp the ſpirits, the ſpirits of a Name and Family,</hi> when the light of it ſhall bee put out,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob</hi> 18 5.</note> and the <hi>ſparkle</hi> of his fire <hi>ſhine no more.</hi> Who knowe's not that God doth often ſcourge the ſinne of the Father in the children? and, for the foule<note n="a" place="margin">The crimes here mencio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n'd, were Aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Sacriledge; which (ſpoken only in <hi>communi,</hi> and as a poſitiue truth in Diuinitie) the miſpriſion, or preiudice of ſome did wire-draw and reſtraine too perſonally; and brought-home that to particular Families, which was intended only ingenerall, and at large. And therefore, if there bee any boſome ſo guiltie, as to eutertaine them otherwiſe, I am ſorrie for the Application: the Authour is innocent.</note> obliquities of the Predeceſſour, ſet's a <hi>rot</hi> vpon the whole <hi>Poſteritie,</hi> when the <hi>name</hi> ſhall moulder with
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18696:21"/>the <hi>Bodie,</hi> and the <hi>Fortunes</hi> with the <hi>name;</hi> ſo that the <hi>curſe</hi> againſt the wicked man, runn's double; firſt, againſt his <hi>fortunes;</hi> they ſhall <hi>dry vp as a riuer,</hi> and <hi>ſhall vanniſh with noyſe like a great thunder in vaine;</hi> next on his <hi>Iſſue;</hi> they <hi>ſhall not bring forth branches,</hi> but are as <hi>vncleane roots vpon a hard rocke. Eccleſ.</hi> 40.13, 15. Here is a <hi>vanè conturbaris,</hi> indeed; and not barely ſo, but, an <hi>infructuosè conturbaris,</hi> alſo; not only a <hi>vaine anxietie,</hi> but a <hi>fruitleſſe;</hi> for, here is neither a <hi>theſaurizas,</hi> nor a <hi>congregabis;</hi> no Riches left that were heapt vp; or (if there bee) <hi>none to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus, they that ſow <hi>vanitie</hi> ſhall reape the <hi>winde;</hi> not a <hi>winde</hi> that ſhall lull and whiſtle them, but a <hi>winde</hi> that driue's and ſcatter's; ſcatters them, as the chaffe from the face of the whole earth. And though they grow mightie in poſſeſſion, or name; ſo mightie, that in height they reach the very cloud's, yet God <hi>ſhall perſecute them with his tempeſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.12.</note> 
                  <hi>and make them afraid with his ſtorme; at his preſence, theſe cloudes ſhall be remoued;</hi> and then, <hi>haileſtones,</hi> and coales of <hi>fire.</hi> Or, though they aſpire not ſo high, but climbe the mountaines only (though ſome mountaines (they ſay) kiſſe the cloudes, too) yet, <hi>tangit montes, &amp; fumigabunt,</hi> God ſhall touch thoſe mountaines, and they ſhall ſmoake; and as they ſmoake, vaniſh, and vaniſhing, confeſſe <hi>Tuſolus al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsimus ſuper omnem terram.</hi> Thou, O Lord, art a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue thoſe mountaines, and not only aboue them, but all the World beſide.</p>
               <p>And I could wiſh that my words were altogether
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18696:22"/>at randome here; and look't not <hi>collaterally,</hi> both to the <hi>text</hi> and the occaſion. Who ſee's not (and let me not be thought rough, or vncharitable, in that I ſay, who ſee's not) that in latter ages <hi>the Almightie's Beſome</hi> hath beene here; and, in the circuite of a few yeares, ſwept away many <hi>braue Worthies</hi> of the <hi>name;</hi> and not only his <hi>Beſome,</hi> but his <hi>Axe</hi> too, lopt off many a <hi>hopefull twig,</hi> and <hi>glorious branch;</hi> and now of late, ſtrooke at the<note n="b" place="margin">The Roote (howeuer) is ſtill greene; &amp; I wiſh heartily that it may grow-vp, and bud, &amp; branch, to the flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitie of the Name; though ſome haue barkt at my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegritie, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king my words here, a chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh prophecie, of the extirpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it, and ſinall doome. But ſuch ſnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and cloſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biters of mens honours, I muſtproclaime ignorant, or vniuſt, or both; for, either they vnderſtood not what I ſpake, or, if they did, were iniurious in their applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Hoc tu Romane caueto.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Stemme,</hi> of the <hi>Family;</hi> and at a blow hewe'd downe, one of the <hi>goodlieſt Cedars</hi> in all our <hi>Libanus.</hi> The very ſtones and walls ſpeake ſo much; thoſe vntimely <hi>Blackes,</hi> and theſe <hi>ſorrowes.</hi> And yet (me thinke's) our ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes are not as they ſhould bee; our <hi>Firre-trees</hi> howle not that their Cedar is fall'n, neither are our Harpes (as yet) hung vpon the willowes; but wee can <hi>ſing</hi> an <hi>Epithalamium,</hi> when we ſhould be ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an <hi>Elegie,</hi> as if our proiects could befoole the <hi>Almighties,</hi> and 'twere in our power to raiſe or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh a <hi>name,</hi> when God ſeeme's to threaten the pulling downe. <hi>But (O thou altogether vanitie)</hi> looke vp to the <hi>Hils</hi> aboue, and to the <hi>Heauens</hi> aboue them; and there, to the <hi>maker</hi> of them both; who ſit's in his great <hi>watch-tower,</hi> and obſerue's all the paſſages of the <hi>ſonnes of men;</hi> and not only obſerue's them, but laugh's them to ſcorne; and, childing our preſumptuous and vaine deſignes, bidd's vs looke backe to the text here; where we may reade the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of our wretchedneſſe, and ſo acknowledge, at length with our Prophet, that, <hi>Thou, O God, haſt made our dayes as a ſpan-long, and that our Age is as nothing
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:18696:22"/>before thee; and ſurely euery man in his beſt ſlate is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together vanitie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I haue done now with the <hi>text,</hi> and ſhould begin with the <hi>occaſion</hi> of it; the death of our <hi>Honourable Friend;</hi> but I was commanded only for a <hi>Sermon,</hi> not for a <hi>Panegyricke,</hi> that (I ſuppoſe) you might haue had (here) in a more keene and accurate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; mine (I confeſſe) like my griefes, heauie, and bedew'd. True ſorrow is more <hi>heartie,</hi> then <hi>Rhetoricall;</hi> and not ſo fit for <hi>applauſe,</hi> as for a <hi>groane.</hi> Your <hi>ſauning</hi> eloquence playe's to much with the tongue, and leaue's the inward man vnſearcht; but, my <hi>boſome</hi> is ingag'd here, and not my <hi>lips;</hi> and that is too full to be emptied in this <hi>ſpan-long</hi> of an <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditorie;</hi> the world ſhall haue it in an impartiall <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niuerſarie:</hi> or, ſhould I vent my <hi>reſpects,</hi> heere I could bee only your <hi>Remembrancer,</hi> not, your <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Country was not ſo much a ſtranger to his worth, but muſt acknowledge <hi>this truth</hi> with me; that hee was not guiltie of any peculiar ſinne, either of <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> or of <hi>youth;</hi> no lofty-ones, of <hi>arrogance</hi> or <hi>ſcorne;</hi> no grinding-ones, of <hi>cruelty</hi> or <hi>oppreſſion;</hi> no flaming-ones, of <hi>ryot,</hi> or of <hi>lust;</hi> no baſe-ones of <hi>anxiety,</hi> or <hi>ſolicitude;</hi> no lewd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones, of <hi>prophanation</hi> or <hi>debauchment;</hi> no bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting-ones, of <hi>rancour,</hi> or <hi>detraction;</hi> no creeping<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ones, of <hi>Inſinuation,</hi> or <hi>popularitie;</hi> no painted-ones, of <hi>ceremony,</hi> or <hi>hypocriſie;</hi> but all his <hi>Actions went by the line,</hi> and the ſquare, as if his life had beene an exact <hi>Epitome</hi> both of <hi>moralitie,</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> There
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:18696:23"/>was nothing <hi>mortall about</hi> him, but his <hi>Body,</hi> and that was too frayle a <hi>cabbonet</hi> for thoſe rich <hi>eminences</hi> to lodge in,<note place="margin">Plin: Paneg.</note> ſo that, as <hi>Plinie</hi> told his <hi>Traian mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas magis finita est, quam vita</hi> his <hi>life</hi> was not termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated, but his <hi>mortality; Goodneſſe</hi> and <hi>vertue</hi> (which were his being) haue a kinde of <hi>Diuinitie</hi> in them; and ſo, not <hi>mortall. Bonus a Deo differt tantum tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Stoicke,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sen. Ep. <hi>73.</hi>
                  </note> Betweene God and a good man, there is no <hi>distinction</hi> but in <hi>time;</hi> nor in that neither, if he meane (as it ſeeme's he do's) a <hi>titularie God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Idem Ibid.</note> not an <hi>eſſentiall;</hi> for, <hi>nulla ſine Deo mens bona,</hi> there is no good minde without a God in it: and that's the reaſon (I thinke) <hi>great men</hi> were firſt cal'd <hi>Gods;</hi> for, <hi>greatneſſe</hi> preſuppoſeth ſome <hi>raritie</hi> and <hi>perfection</hi> in it, and where that is, there is a kind of <hi>God head.</hi> And, if it were euer in <hi>greatneſſe,</hi> it was heere; whether you take <hi>greatneſſe</hi> for the <hi>name,</hi> or for the <hi>ſpirit;</hi> not, that hee was either <hi>haughtie</hi> or <hi>ſupercilious,</hi> but of a temper, <hi>truly generous,</hi> and <hi>heroicke,</hi> and (what is aboue ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) truly <hi>Chriſtian. A fast friend, and a noble brother, A munificent and open-handed Maſter;</hi> and (what I know, and therefore ſpeake, and ſpeake that you ſhould know, and ſo imitate) <hi>an vncorrupted Patron;</hi> no <hi>fire-brand</hi> in his <hi>Countrey,</hi> nor <hi>Meteor</hi> in his <hi>Church;</hi> a flaſh, and falfe-blaze in <hi>Religion,</hi> he was ſo farre from approuing, that hee loathed; neither was hee ſo benighted in his <hi>intellectuals,</hi> as to be led vp and downe in a peruerſe <hi>ignorance</hi> and darkneſſe, by an <hi>Ignis fatuus;</hi> your <hi>vocall puritie,</hi>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:18696:23"/>and <hi>tongue deuotion,</hi> and <hi>furious zeale,</hi> euen when hee was no more a dying <hi>man,</hi> but a <hi>Saint</hi> (and the words of <hi>dying Saints are Oraculous to me</hi>) hee both cenſur'd and diſclaimd; wiſhing the walles of our <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> built vp ſtronger in <hi>Vnity</hi> and <hi>Peace;</hi> and, a more temperate and diſcreet ſilence amongſt the <hi>wayward Hot-ſpurres</hi> of our <hi>Spirituall Mother.</hi> And, indeed, this <hi>Clamorous Sanctitie,</hi> this affected <hi>dreſſe</hi> of <hi>holineſſe, without,</hi> is not the right <hi>dreſſe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prou.</hi> 30.12.</note> 
                  <hi>There is a generation</hi> (ſaith the <hi>Prophet</hi>) <hi>that are pure in their owne eyes, and yet is not waſhed from their filthines;</hi> the <hi>ragge,</hi> or the menſtruous <hi>cloute,</hi> not ſo loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome as ſome of theſe. <hi>Our bodies</hi> (you know) are call'd the <hi>Temples</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt; our heart, the <hi>Altar</hi> of that Temple; true deuotion, the <hi>fire</hi> of that <hi>Altar;</hi> ſighes, and groanes, and ſobs, the <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice</hi> for that fire; Theſe caſt-vp the <hi>acceptable o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour;</hi> theſe, only theſe, the ſweet <hi>incenſe in the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils of the Almightie.</hi> The <hi>Hecatombe,</hi> and out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward pompe of ſacrifice, hath too much of the <hi>beaſt</hi> in it, the many-headed beaſt, the <hi>multitude;</hi> that, <hi>within,</hi> is of the <hi>ſpirit;</hi> and that of the ſpirit, is the true Child's of God; And this our noble friend had, without <hi>gloſſe</hi> or <hi>varniſh,</hi> his <hi>life</hi> a recollected <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianitie;</hi> his ſickneſſe, a penitent <hi>humiliation;</hi> and his <hi>death,</hi> an vnbattered <hi>aſſurance</hi> of his richer eſtate in <hi>glory;</hi> Inſomuch, that I knew not, whether I might enuie, or admire, that God had beſtowed ſuch a plentifull <hi>mortification,</hi> on a <hi>Secular condition, and left Diuinitie, ſo barren.</hi> No <hi>Viper</hi> in his boſome; nor <hi>Vulture</hi> at his heart; no convulſion or gripe of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:18696:24"/>
                  <hi>Conſcience;</hi> no pang of the <hi>inward man</hi> (ſo he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to me) for the <hi>reigue of any darling ſinne.</hi> And (indeed) his priuate meditations, groanes, ſolilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quies, penſiue eleuations of eyes, and ſpirit, rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's full of <hi>ſublimitie,</hi> and <hi>contemplation</hi> (ſuch as the heart could only eiaculate, and not the tongue) vndaunted <hi>reſolutions</hi> and defiance of <hi>death,</hi> and all her terrours, ſpake him gloriſied, before hee died. And thus, hauing made a full peace with God, and with the world, he ſang his <hi>Nunc dimittis,</hi> and made a willing ſurrender of his Soule into the hands of his <hi>Redeemer;</hi> where hee hath now his <hi>Palme and white Robe, his Pennie of true happineſſe,</hi> and <hi>Crowne of euer laſting glorie;</hi> to which God bring vs, with him, for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>Gloria in Excelſis Deo.</closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:18696:24"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
